All right, so let's just start, we'll
start by recapping a little bit from
what we ended with two weeks ago
and then we'll get into tonight. So
we discussed the we are discussing within
the world of Yayin Nesach what actually
makes the wine aser what what do
you have to do to make it
aser. We discussed already some of the
criteria for who is considered a goy
who is not considered the Muslims the
Christians things like that. Oh, sorry, yeah.
So sponsoring the learning tonight is being
sponsored by Dovid Yaakov and Leah Liba
Elka, Rabbi Dovid Radinsky, who is having
had a surgery this afternoon so all
the learning should be a refuah sheleimah.
Okay, so we mentioned in the Shulchan
Aruch, we won't go back through it,
but we mentioned in in Sif Yud
and in Yud Aleph in Kuf Chaf
Daled. Again, this is just a review
from a few weeks ago because it's
important to have some review. That the
non-Jew has to intend to want to
touch the wine, that was condition number
one. He has to know that he
is touching wine, that is number two.
He has to not be distracted, has
to be focused on the fact that
he's touching wine, and he has to
actually shake the wine. Those are the
four criteria in Yud Aleph says it
as well, so intent to touch the
wine, knowledge that it's wine, focus, and
the fact that he's actually shaking it.
We learned this chidush of the Rema
in... yeah, we learned the chidush of
the Rema that the Rema basically says
that... hold on. Yeah, so if we
go to Sif Yud Ches again, this
is still chazarah. If you go to
Sif Yud Ches. Okay, if you go
to Sif Yud Ches, the Shulchan Aruch
here, based on a Gemara in Avodah
Zarah that talks about pouring the wine
without even shaking the wine, would be
potentially a problem. Here the Rema in
Yud Tes, which we saw last time...
just thinking if we should do inside/outside...
no. Okay, so the... hold on, let
me go to one more Shulchan Aruch.
Yeah, go to Kuf Chaf Daled, this
is where we ended with the Rema.
So the Rema here, according to a
number of Rishonim, has this big, big
chidush. The Rema in Kuf Chaf Daled
tells us that in the end of
the day le-ma'aseh really it's not such
a problem. All of this that we
discussed, not such a problem. Why? Because
the Rema says הוא הדין אם הכניס,
I'm sorry, in the middle... אם נגע
ביין על ידי דבר אחר. So if
you do it unintentionally, you're, you know,
like the waiter and the stick that
goes in, he wasn't focused and things
like that. Since everything dumbs down a
level, so it's not such a big
deal. And the Rema then says that's
really the situation today. That that if
a... the Rema says that even if
the non-Jew really directly touches the wine,
that's not really going to be such
a problem today. However, we don't really
want to be mefarsem, he says at
the end, we don't really want to
tell the non-Jews about this big chidush
that we have, but it does seem
that a very, very big chidush that
if a Christian were to pour out
a glass of kosher wine without directly
touching the wine, you would be allowed
to drink it. That's what the Rema
says. That's a big, big chidush. We
just went through three weeks telling you
that it should be aser, that a
non-Jew, a Christian, that's avodah zarah if
there's ever avodah zarah. And yet the
Rema says really today everybody's really not
it's not they're not so bad. And
if they... since we know that indirectly
is okay, so today basically everything should
be not a problem at all, but
ואין לפרסם הדבר בפני עמי הארץ. Don't
let everybody know about this. Yet today
we're pretty machmir about this. We do
not seem to follow this leniency of
the Rema. So tonight is going to
figure out a little bit about the
rest of this topic. Why are we
machmir? Who are we machmir about? When
are we machmir? So let's review the
following. Okay, if you look at קכ\"ה
א. Okay, that is the next siman,
קכ\"ה א. There the Rema says... I'm
sorry, the Shulchan Aruch says that wine
that is poured by a non-Jew, okay,
that is aser to drink. It could
benefit, but it says נטל עובד כוכבים
כלי שיש בו יין והגביהו והציק יין.
If he takes it, אף על פי
שלא שכשו, ne'esar bi-shtiyah. You cannot drink
that wine שהרי היין בא מכחו. We'll
come back to this later about nitzok
in a second. You could benefit from
it, but whatever is left in the
kli is going to be a... you
can't drink it, but at least you
can benefit from it. Says the Rema...
ויש אומרים דלא אסרינן ניצוק בכח עובד
כוכבים. The Rema disagrees as he does
earlier and the Rema says it's fine.
Why is it fine? Because מכל מקום
יש להחמיר אם לא הפסד מרובה. It's
better to be machmir if you don't
if you don't need to, but in
the end it seems to be that
you could be meikel about it as
well. The Shach right here in se'if
katan alef on the right side, so
the Shach has a question. The Shach
says: Hold on a second. Earlier the
Rema says it seems to be permitted.
Here he's saying really only if it's
a case of significant loss. So the
Rema explains the following: קשיא דלעיל סימן
קכ\"ד סעיף י\"ד פסק דמה שנשאר בפנים
מותר. Earlier we learned the Rema's like:
Ah, everything's fine! Even what's left in
the bottle! והיינו משום דלא חמירו כמו
בניצוק. Nitzok is a concept we'll come
back to tonight of pouring. So since
the kli is assur, whatever came out
of the kli connects what's out of
the kli and in the kli, so
whatever is left in the kli is
assur. The Rema said before it's muttar.
I don't understand! וכן לקמן סימן קכ\"ח
העתיק לשון הטור דיוצא אסור בשתייה משמע
דמה שבפנים מותר. I don't understand! And
now we're saying unless it's a real
case of loss you should be machmir.
ve-kashya de-nitzok. He has another question. So
he says in the few lines below:
ולדידן הכל שרי במקום הפסד. He explains
that the Rema is only leaning when
there's a great loss of money because
either he says דכל מה שאסור מן
הדין בשתייה. When we say that you
can't drink it, לדידן דעובד כוכבים בזמן
הזה, but today since I hold, says
the Shach for the Rema, that all
the Goyim today are לאו עובדי כוכבים
הם שרי אף בשתייה. So really, really
the Shach is saying: No, the Rema
meant what he said. The Rema meant
what he said. It's okay to be
machmir if one wants to but really
in the end of the day the
Shach is saying what the Rema holds
and this is why coming back to
what we ended with last week, two
weeks ago, that according to the Rema
really it should be okay but we're
machmir when it seems if there's not
a big loss. Okay. Now go back
to the end of yod-chet. Okay. Go
back to the end of yod-chet. So
the Rema—the Shulchan Aruch here says the
following: נטל עובד כוכבים כלי של יין.
If a Goy takes a bottle of
wine ve-higbiho ve-yatzak ha-yayin. He lifts it
and he pours it. He doesn't shake
it. Okay? He's very careful. נאסר שהרי
יין מכחו. הגביהו ולא שכסכו ולא נגע
מותר. So the Shulchan Aruch says that
if he merely lifts it without shaking
or pouring it nothing's assur. Okay? הגביהו
ולא שכסכו ולא נגע מותר. The Rema
says וכל שכן שאינו אוסר בנגיעת הכלי
לחוד. So just meaning because we're meikel
about these Goyim if I pick it
up, the Goy picks it up, doesn't
move it, doesn't touch, doesn't touch the
wine, doesn't shake it, doesn't pour, he
just lifts it up, that would be
okay, number one. Number two, the Rema
adds that just touching the bottle of
wine is going to be okay. Right?
It's going to be okay. The Shach—there's
a very short Shach here in siman
mem-gimmel right on the left side. So
the Shach wants in the—the Shach says:
Hold on a second. ולכן אני תמה
על קצת המחמירים ומפסידים ממון של ישראל
לאסור יין שנגע בו עובד כוכבים. I
don't understand! Why is everybody machmir about
it? The Rema's seemingly meikel about it.
So he says ולכן נראה דאין לחוש
כלל. Really we should say that it
should be muttar completely. Let's just finish
a little bit of this. If you
go to siman yod-zayin—we're going backwards—go to
siman yod-zayin, I'm sorry. Says the Shulchan
Aruch in siman yod-zayin if he shakes
the wine without lifting it: היה שם
ואחז עובד כוכבים בכלי פתוח של יין
ושכסכו ואף על פי שלא הגביהו. He—it's
there on the counter. He shakes it
but he doesn't lift it ולא נגע
ביין אסור. Then it would be assur.
The Rema says ve-yesh harbe cholkim. And
many, many are—argue that, you know, without
lifting the glass is not really a
problem. Why? Because the whole issue of
lifting and pouring is that's how they
did Avoda Zara. They didn't do the
Avoda Zara with it being on the
counter. Okay. How big of a difference
does that make? Ah, okay. So then
says the Shulchan Aruch and this is
just—this will wrap up until we get
into some more practical stuff. If you
go to kuf-kaf-hey-tet. Okay? kuf-kaf-hey-tet. We're going
to talk about clothes also a little
bit later. So the Shulchan Aruch here...
it says which we'll do it outside
that a closed bottle right if you
look in the Shach the Shach talks
about sosum. So a closed bottle does
not become forbidden even if it's shaken
by a goy. Okay so a closed
bottle does not become assur even if
it's shaken by a goy. העובד כוכבים
שנטל של יין what? The Shulchan Aruch
says ונטלו ממקום למקום שאוחז פי הנוד
בידו בין שהיה מלא או חסר מותר
even though it's moving around. He schlepped
it around. So he says why? Says
the Shach explains because it's closed. דאם
לא כן אסור משום שכשוך it can't
be assur because of shikhshukh only. Since
it's closed we are we're more lenient
about it. And that means re-closed also
right? Hold on hold on hold on.
So fine. So let's let's review. So
again we had four criteria. You had
to have intent to touch the wine
that a person is touching. So therefore
if somebody accidentally you know touched the
wine would it be a problem? Number
two was that I have to have
knowledge that I know that I'm touching
this wine that you know again a
person thinks they're pouring you know I
don't know honey and it's wine it
would be a problem. They had to
have focus the whole time and they
have to be able to to shake
it. Okay. Fine. You can go through
in the notes later all these different
things about you know they have a
good chart. Okay. Fine. Go to the
booklet for a second. Okay so the
Chazon Ish here in source seventeen says
that he's not so sure about the
kullah of the Rema. So the Chazon
Ish he's quoting the Taz. The Taz
will become a very important Taz as
we move on tonight because the Taz
based on the Rambam holds that whenever
a non-Jew I don't care if the
non-Jew is a law-abiding Christian Protestant Catholic
doesn't matter Buddhist Muslim a non-Jew that
touches the wine says the Taz is
assur. Says the Chazon Ish כתב דכוחו
אף על גב דקיימא לן דמותר בהנאה
מכל מקום לא נסמיכין חד דרגא לדידן
להתיר בשתיה. He says it can't be
that we even though we might reduce
it by a level it can't be
that it's reduced to a level that
it's mutar to drink. And he quotes
from the Rebbi Akiva Eiger הסכים עם
השך דלדידן מותר בשתיה he writes that
the Rebbi Akiva Eiger and quoting the
Dugul Mervava and the Shach all disagree
with this Taz and they allow drinking
מכל מקום לדידן מותר בשתיה כיון דאז
מלאה של כוונת ניסוך כמורא של בלי
כוונה דמותר בשתיה. So he says the
Taz we're going to see tonight you're
right the Taz is going to argue
on the Rema. This is going to
be a huge Taz because even though
generally we follow a Shach and everybody
else one of the reasons we are
going to find that we are more
machmir for some of these things even
though Shach Rebbi Akiva Eiger Dugul Mervava
the Shach himself said I don't know
why everybody's being meikel about this. We're
going to find reasons that that more
contemporary poskim are machmir about it. So
in the end of the day sof
kol sof if you stopped here it
would seem that everybody that the Rema
is meikel. If the Rema is meikel
Rebbi Akiva Eiger is meikel Dugul Mervava
is meikel the except the Taz. So
that a non-Jew today it would dumb
it down a level that basically every
time a non-Jew would touch your wine
it's the level of like no no
intention to it and therefore it would
it would be potentially for sure mutar
be-hana'ah and potentially even mutar be-shtiya. Okay?
That's that's what the halacha says. You
don't find that many areas of halacha
where like it's pretty clear that it's
one way and yet we're going to
find like we're machmir about this. We're
machmir about this. No we we don't
find like a kashrut agency out there
that will you know in Israel this
is a big shaila with waiters and
things like that. Who can be a
waiter? We don't find kashrut agencies that
are like oh it's fine he's a
Christian that's fine he can touch wine.
We're pretty machmir about it. So let's
see. Okay. Now. So again the Shulchan
Aruch would hold that everybody could at
least benefit the Rema would seem to
hold that everybody could at least drink
it. So there's three levels. Shulchan Aruch
says מותר בהנאה אסור בשתיה the Rema
says mutar be-shtiya and the Shach says
that the Rema's mutar in drinking is
only makom hefsed. It's fine but like
don't always rely on it. Okay. That
would be when it comes to a
Christian. When it comes to a Muslim
leaving out the Taz for a second
when it comes to a Muslim the
Shulchan Aruch would say what? What would
Shulchan Aruch say about a Muslim? You
could drink it. He's not a goy
right? The Dugul Mervava and the Shach
everybody else would seem to everybody else
would seemingly agree. So the question is:
Why are we machmir by the Muslims
more than we would have based on
these halachos? Okay. Fine. Good. Versteh'st. Let's
go. So look at Rav Moshe Feinstein.
So there's a tshuva of Rav Moshe.
Okay, again, the Shulchan Aruch would never
allow drinking of wine poured by Christians,
okay? That would be assur, assur, assur.
You cannot drink that wine. If the
guy, your workmate, Christensen, very good, what
are we going to do with that,
okay, if he comes to your party
and pours your bottle of wine, you
cannot drink that wine. So the question
was asked to Rav Moshe, can a
catering company hire non-Jewish waiters, non-Jewish workers,
okay, and have them pouring wine using
gloves? Ah, if I wear gloves, everything's
fine. The Christian didn't touch your wine,
the gloves touched your wine. Okay. So
Rav Moshe writes, now number one he
says in the first paragraph, gloves don't
help. Okay, so let's forget about that.
Gloves don't really help because it's actually
considered touching and it wouldn't really help.
He says there in that second paragraph
negi'ah beyado mamash, that's like exactly touching
with your hands. Okay. So then he
writes in the next paragraph, he says,
let's go to the bottom. הא דאיתא
בריש סימן קכ\"ד בעכו\"ם שהגביה כלי של
יין ויצא יין שזהו שצריך לאסור בשתייה
ואם הוא שלא בכוונה מותר שכן איתא
בש\"ך. Like we just saw, דבזמן הזה
שרי אפילו שלא במקום הפסד ממון לא
הוי כהאי דנחשב נגיעה בזמן הזה שלא
בכוונה. That's the Rema. The Rema says
that touching the wine today is like
it didn't have intention, which means that
it should be mutar. לעניין נגיעה על
ידי דבר אחר יש מקום להתיר אף
בלא בדיעבד. If you hold like the
Rema, well then I don't need gloves.
דאיתא בש\"ך דוקא במקום הפסד יש לסמוך
על זה. So Rav Moshe says really
only in a place of loss. In
the end of the day, though, Rav
Moshe says, I don't think you should
do this, and let's see why. ואם
כן שייך זה רק שאירע דרך מקרה.
This is all assuming like things are
happening randomly so to speak, or not
so frequently. But the Shach and the
Rema don't mean that I can hire
a non-Jew on a permanent basis to
be the guy pouring wine. You want
to say that once in a while
it happened, we can use that Rema.
That's number one, says Rav Moshe. אבל
לכתחילה לא שייך להתיר אף להרמ\"א שאסור
לכתחילה. The Rema wouldn't say that. The
Rema wouldn't say that. Second of all,
he says, וגם הכא יש לאסור אף
בדיעבד מדינא אף להרמ\"א שצריך להשגיח בכל
עת ממש. Forget anything, you have a
problem when you have unattended wine bottles.
That's a problem in kashrus. Okay, if
you, you know, you left the room
and all of a sudden you came
back and all your workers were there,
so he says, Rav Moshe, it's not
such a good idea, not such a
good idea. Okay, again, the Rema's not
wrong. We hold by that Rema, but
we're not really going to rely on
it for sure on a permanent lechatchila
basis to hire, you know, Arab workers
let's say. Okay. It doesn't matter. It
doesn't matter. Well they can't pour closed
bottles. It's the gravity. What if it's—they
didn't open it, it's just in the
office and they didn't open it till—what
are you hiring them for? They're not
waiters. They're carrying around—Schleppers. Yeah, you could
hire them to schlep. So how does
this impact, I mean, maybe we'll get
there, bedi'eved keilim? Okay, good. Good. Hold
on. So bedi'eved there's what to meikel
on. There's what to meikel on. Especially
in a place of loss. But we'll
see, we'll see. Again, how hard is
it to kasher a thing? It's probably
not so hard. Sometimes it's annoying to
kasher, but it's not a hefsed merubeh.
Okay, fine. Yeah. So we'll see, we'll
see in a second. Okay, so if
you remember, if you go back to
קכ\"ד ז. We're not going to see
it inside, just a reminder if you
want to see it, you go to
קכ\"ד ז. The Shulchan Aruch here in
קכ\"ד ז mentioned the following: He said
that יש אוסרים בכל מקום שאסרו ביין
שלנו שמותר בהנאה. That whenever there is
contact by a non-Jew when it comes
to these issues of wine... Muslim, it
should really be okay and certainly a
mechallel Shabbos befarhesia should be okay. So
the question is, where does it come
today that we're machmir about these? And
we are machmir about mechallel Shabbos befarhesia
also. Now, maybe not to the point
as we'll see to embarrass somebody, but
we are machmir that if a person
came to your home who is a
straight mechallel Shabbos befarhesia—not they didn't forget
tinok shenishba, they knew what they were
doing, they drove to your house on
Shabbos, they honked the horn, they promoted
it haya machanecha kadosh and they got
to your house and they take your
bottle of wine and they pour it,
we're machmir. And the question is why?
We just saw from the Rama that
we shouldn't be machmir about these things.
So why are we machmir? So it
could be one answer is we're like
the Taz, because the Taz is a
machmir. I'm sorry, the Taz is a
meikel, the Taz is machmir. So that's
number one. But so the reason to
be a little bit more machmir is
the following. So now let's go for
a little bit of background, we're gonna
do the following. Okay. Go to source
19. So here's the topic, the concept
of what we said before of nitzuk.
There's another halacha that relates to stam
yeinam and that is the concept of
nitzuk. Nitzuk means a stream that a
stream of wine that is poured has
a halachic connection between the container that
the wine is in and the container
that the cup or whatever the wine
is going into. So the Gemara says
in source 19 that אמר ליה רב
חסדא לאנהו סבותא. So Rav Huna, I'm
sorry, Rav Chisda would instruct his wine
merchants that when they're filling bottles belonging
to non-Jews that they should ensure כי
חליתו חמרא (it's cut off there) אלא
כטיפי כטוף. Really what they should do
is they should pour it in short
bursts. Short bursts from an elevated position
and not to have one long stream.
So if they are filling bottles belonging
to non-Jews, what's Rav Chisda worried about?
Nitzuk. I have my kli of wine,
you have a kli that's a problem.
If I pour from my cup into
from my vat into your cup, well,
it's connecting the two and it's gonna
asser whatever is left in my barrel
or whatever. What's the fancy thing people
put on their tables to pour wine
out of? Decanter. Very good. Very good.
Okay, so Rav Chisda said don't do
that. Rather do like this. If you
do it like this, that's okay, because
that's not really connecting anything. That's why
we tell people when they're kashering, don't
do this. You can't a little bit,
a little bit, a little bit, you
have to kasher again. It has to
be nitzuk, it has to be a
stream because you can only kasher in
a kli rishon. So if I had
a boiling pot of water and I
poured a little bit and then I
stopped and I poured a little bit
and then I stopped, it's a question
of does that consider nitzuk or not.
So Rashi here on the left side,
Rashi says that he explains this concept
with Rav Chisda and Tosafot, I'm sorry,
this Tosafot, Tosafot says that nitzuk is
not really such a problem. Says Rabbeinu
Tam, no, nitzuk is okay. It's not
a problem. How do we pasken? So
go into Kuf Chaf Vav now and
it was a little bit all over
the place tonight. If you go to
קוף כף ו\"ו א\"ל\"ף. Okay. So the
Shulchan Aruch in קוף כף ו\"ו א\"ל\"ף
paskens like that Gemara that if you're
pouring wine העירוי מכלי שיש בו יין
עובד כוכבים אסור בהנאה נאסר כל היין
שבכלי העליון and it would be a
problem. If I'm pouring from my bottle
of Kedem grape juice into your avoda
zara cup, my whole Kedem grape juice
is now a problem. שהעמוד הניצוק מחבר
בין היין שבכלי העליון לבין היין שבכלי
התחתון, that's all mixed together והוי כאילו
יין של איסור מעורב בשל היתר. But
אם אירה בקיטוף שקודם שנגע בשל איסור
הפסיק קילוחו היורד מהיין של היתר מותר.
So we pasken exactly like this, Shulchan
Aruch paskens exactly like the Gemara says.
In seif daled, the Shulchan Aruch explains
הדין ניצוק חיבור הני מילי בהפסד מועט,
that there is a chumra but it
only apply again if it's not a
big loss. If it's a big loss,
we might be a little bit meikel.
The Shach right here in seif katan
aleph, the Shach explains the Shulchan Aruch
is machmir only, says the following, quotes
the Rambam. And he says אלא שהחמיר
המחבר בדבר ואסור בהנאה והוציא היין שאינו
אסור אלא בשתיה לא שייך בו ניצוק.
It's only nitzuk when the actual wine
that is in the bottom cup is
asser. If I want to say that
I'm connecting something that is mutter that's
mine, something asser that's yours, your thing
has to be asser. Well, that's gonna
depend on Who's holding it and what
the status of this cup is and
what kind of religion he professes to
be a part of. See, so it
depends. Now, according to the shita of
the Rama before nitzok? Correct, correct, correct.
Okay, now, now, it's a lot of
background. I'm not sure they have this
way, but either way take out the
book and now go to source twenty-one.
Okay so now go to source twenty-one.
So the, Joel's point is correct. Meaning
what we learned earlier that this should
be bedieved? So here the Ateret Shlomo
quotes the Tiferet Adam and the Beit
Yehuda. דכיוון שרבים אוסרים את היוצא בכוחו
גם בהנאה שיטת הרמב\"ם הוא דמהי. Since
there are those like the Rama and
who else? The Taz. הנה אף על
פי שלעניין הפסד היין פסק מרן להתיר
בהנאה את היוצא. That you're right. We
do accept that opinion of the Rama.
And that opinion of the Rama says
that any non-Jew prohibits that wine to
drink or to benefit from. מכל מקום
לעניין היתר שתייה לא התיר וחשש לאסור
את ההנאה מדין ניצוק. But we are
going to be concerned. If you're telling
me that I know that there are
those that are meikel but the Rama
is machmir, then we are going to
be machmir when it comes to nitzok.
And he says on the left side,
מכל מקום לכאורה יש להקל במה שהוציא
מכוח בשתייה. The Sefer Ataret Shlomo is
explaining the Shulchan Aruch really says this
wine is assur. It's assur. Are there
times that we're lenient? Yeah, we are.
But we're not going to be lenient
when it comes to nitzok. It's the
same thing. So really we're going to
be machmir. So that, that's number one.
That maybe because of nitzok that connects
something that's assur to something that's mutar,
we're going to be machmir. Fine, that's
number one. Number two. How about a
Muslim? Okay, what about a Muslim? We
never had a sichat chavurah context where
we said the word Muslim this many
times. Look in the Yabia Omer. Okay,
so says Rav Ovadia. Says Rav Ovadia.
זכות באר מים מעתה דברים קל וחומר
בקיצור שבוודאי שאינו אוסר מדין ניצוק מה
שנשאר בצלוחית העליונה. No, that you're right.
The wine poured by a Muslim you
can drink. Okay, but there is benefit
that we can get from it and
therefore nitzok does not apply. מותר אפילו
בשתייה ורק שם מה ששפך לכוס יש
להחמיר ולאסור בשתייה. So Rav Ovadia paskens
that no, that it would be okay.
You can drink what's left and nitzok
does not forbid what was left in
the thing, right? So that's Rav Ovadia
about a Muslim. And the same is
true in source twenty-two in the Sefer
Yayin LeNesach. It's a great name of
a Sefer. Okay, Sefer Yayin LeNesach paskens
the same thing in source twenty-two. And
he says that majority of Sephardi poskim
though still say that they allow drinking
of wine poured by a Muslim, but
he writes in the second column it's
just in interest of time, לכתחילה נכון
להחמיר ולהיזהר בכוחו של ישמעאלי. Still be
machmir. ולא יניחו לישמעאלי למזוג יין לכוסם.
You shouldn't have them pour it. דיעבד
שעבר ומזג מותר היין. But if he
poured it, it would be okay. And
the same would be true for a
Mechalel Shabbat. So again we are pretty,
what? Yeah. We go to forty-seven weddings
a year at Ateres Ayala and the
guy pouring the wine, does that affect
this? Correct. Correct. But it's mevuashal? Stam
mevuashal. That wine is mevuashal. Yeah. I
don't think you're bringing a non-mevuashal wine
there. And every caterer has that din?
No. Most kashrus organizations will not allow
to have a non-mevuashal event unless there
are separate mashgiachim. Like you can have
the kashrus are hosting an event catered
by somebody within the cRc hashgacha and
you want to have non-mevuashal wine, you
would need to hire a separate mashgiach
who will pour push the cart himself
and only be the one to pour
the wine. They will not let it
at a bar. For this reason. The
Rama's meikel about it but everybody else
is machmir about it. So again this
comes back to this same issue. The
Rama allows drinking wine poured by a
Muslim. He allows, and he permits wine
that's poured by a Christian. So why
are we machmir? And furthermore, if you
look in source twenty-three, Rav Moshe himself
says it's very, very hard to define
a Mechalel Shabbat Befarhesya. How do you
define such a thing? He says, I'll
know it when you see it. Something
like that. It's hard to give a
metric for something like this. Meaning, the
again, the guy who doesn't know anything,
it's not his fault. The guy who
only knows a certain amount of things,
maybe not his fault. He says in
the middle, he says ובשביל זה בביאורו
hizkir Shulchan Aruch, there is no criteria
listed for this. It's not listed in
the, in the Shach, אם כן משמע
שלא מבואר איסור ממש ועל כל פנים
לדינא נהגו שלא לשתות יין שנהגו בישראל
מומר לחלל שבת בפרהסיא, right? It's not
entirely clear how to define a Mechalel
Shabbos B'Farhesia. It's not codified anywhere. What
about the mumar definition, someone who's l'hachis
as opposed to? Yeah, but I'm saying
that term is very hard to define.
How do you know? You asked last
week about the guy who's off the
derech, is that l'hachis? Maybe you could
argue it's not l'hachis, it's like his
path back, who knows. Strayed away, he
strayed away from. Right, so that's not
l'hachis. Right, right, right. I mean, l'hachis
would, you know, that's not a mumar.
I got a call about a shidduch
for somebody, and the girl called me
about a shidduch for another, like a
friend of hers. And when I reached
out to this guy, I haven't spoken
to him in a very long time,
but I said to him, I said,
she said he doesn't need like the
most religious person, I said he's an
atheist. Like he's mamash, like he went
off. Like maybe a guy who grew
up like mamash frum and like decided
he doesn't believe in anything, maybe, I
don't know, I don't know. So fine,
so again, if the Shach and the
Rema and Rabbi Akiva Eiger and the
Noda B'Yehuda are all meikal, so why
are we machmir? So there are, we'll
see, there's a few others, but there's
a few reasons to be machmir. Let's
go to the Tzitz Eliezer in source
24. How about the Rema, this shitta
of the Rema? Is it davka like
if you made the wine, it was
kosher with Jewish people making the wine,
and then the non-Jew pours it? Or
would it extend, meaning if you take
him l'shito, how does that impact like
the whole sugia of stam yeinam? What
do you mean? Meaning like, if the
wine's made by a non-Jew, there's no
problem according to this Rema? Correct, wouldn't
be a problem. Right. So like there
just wouldn't be the kashrut, it would
just go away. Potentially, potentially, yeah. Okay,
and does anyone bring that as a
snif hakol for our task? No, not
really, not really. Okay, so again, reason
number one is you have the Taz.
You have the Taz and the Rambam
that are machmir by every single non-Jew.
Okay, that's number one. Says the Tzitz
Eliezer in source 24, he brings some
reasons to defend the custom that we're
machmir about it. He says הכל מדובר
כששכשך שלא בכוונה. This whole institution, this
whole idea we're discussing is when because
the Rema's basically saying that any time
a non-Jew touches your wine, it's shelo
b'kavana. Says the Tzitz Eliezer אבל כשהגביה
משכשך בכוונה כדי לשתות יין. The guy's
job was hired as to pour the
wine דבזה אין מי שהתיר אפילו במקום
פסידא. He says that, that doesn't make
sense. Meaning, if he deliberately pours a
glass of wine, that's not shelo b'kavana,
that's pouring wine, and therefore we should
be machmir. The Rema wasn't talking about
any of that. The Rema's saying it
happens to be that he touches it,
it's not so bad. But if I
hire the Muslim to pour the wine,
that is the definition of, you know,
yayin nesech, that's how they did the
libations, was they poured it, so we
should be machmir. That's says, that's the
Tzitz Eliezer. Fine. And what about the
remaining wine in the bottle? So what
would we say about the remaining wine
in the bottle? So says Rav Shlomo
Zalman. Okay, if you go to Rav
Shlomo Zalman, now it seemed to be
that we should say it should be
fine the rest of the wine in
the bottle. However, if you look in
Rav Shlomo Zalman in source 25, Rav
Shlomo Zalman says no. Says הנה כתב
דאין ניצוק חיבור שייך בישמעאל אף שאינו
עובד אלילים. So first he says this
whole idea of nitzok is not part
of the Arabs, she'eino oveid elilim, they
don't worship avoda zara. לכן הסיק שמה
שבתוך הבקבוק מותר אף בשתייה. So if
he poured it, you're right, it should
be a problem but not what's left
in the bottle ורק מה שנשפך לתוך
הכוס אסור בשתייה אולם מרן חולק עליו.
The Sefer Rav Shlomo Zalman was machmir
שנהגו להחמיר בנכרי אף שאינו עובד עבודה
זרה, that he is, Rav Shlomo Zalman
is machmir and says that if it
was poured by a Muslim, whatever remained
in the bottle is assur. Assur. If
you go to the next page, they
quote from Rav Elyashiv. Same thing. They
quote Rav Elyashiv, not only that, he
says he goes one step further. Mechalel
Shabbos shavar yayin bakbuk, so the guy
comes, he's a mechalel shabbos, he takes
the wine, he pours it, אי אפשר
לסמוך על הש\"ך. Don't rely on the
Shach ולהתיר מה שנשאר בבקבוק ואסור לשתות
את זה אם כן מחלל שבת הוא
בפרהסיא. If he's a Mechalel Shabbos B'Farhesia,
it is going to be a problem.
So again, even though the Rema and
the Shach and the Noda B'Yehuda and
Rabbi Akiva Eiger are meikal, we are
machmir. about this halacha. We are machmir
about this halacha. Why would we machmir
about this halacha? So in source 27,
they quote in the name of Rav
Shlomo Zalman the following. We only seem
to assur the stuff that comes out
of the bottle. Now we're saying what's
in the bottle? כותב שם הגאון רב
שלמה זלמן אוירבך שנוהגים להחמיר אף בנוכרי
שאינו בעובד עבודה זרה. He's machmir about
a goy who's not even a terrible
avoda zara. וכגון ישמעאל שיין הבא מכוחו
נאסר. So therefore they would assur the
wine that was poured by a Muslim.
ולכן אם מזג מבקבוק לכוס מה שבכוס
נאסר ואף מה שבבקבוק אסור. And he
says even what's inside is assur. וכן
נראה דעת הציץ אליעזר. But he says
v'divreihem tzrichim iyun. Now whenever you have
somebody who ends v'divreihem tzrichim iyun, it's
a big question. And apparently it's shared
that they're not sure that Rav Elyashiv
actually said this. They don't know and
it's not, it's been reported in his
name but maybe not being so accurate.
Okay. Either way, let's finish off with
one more. And that is the Avnei
Nezer in source 28. Okay? So whether
or not Rav Elyashiv did say it,
he didn't say it, we'll have to
figure that out. Okay. Somebody spoke about
that right, right. Okay. Says the Avnei
Nezer the following. אומנם מחלל שבת אין
בו קולא שלא בכוונה. First he says
that, you know, when it comes to
m'challel shabbos they don't have that kula.
אם כן חזר דינו כיוון שאסר יין
במגעו. Since it's assur for him to
touch it. אם כן גם מה שנשפך
לכוס נאסר משום כוחו וגם מה שנמצא
בתוך הבקבוק אין להתיר רק בהפסד מרובה.
Whatever he poured in is going to
be assur and whatever's left inside, אין
להתיר רק בהפסד מרובה. Why? Because when
the Rema said this, וכן זה לא
אם לא הרים המחלל שבת את הבקבוק,
the Rema was when things were done
without intention. But this is done with
intention. So even though there might not
be a problem of real nisuch, of
real like whatever avoda zara things that
they're doing with the wine, says the
Avnei Nezer and others that we are
going to be machmir. So in the
end of the day, there are reasons
to be meikel. Reasons to be meikel,
wine poured by non-religious Jew, we said
many poskim, Shach, Rabbi Akiva Eiger, that
take one second back. Binyan Tzion and
everybody else, all those people are considered
tinok shenishba let's say. That's idea number
one. That maybe today most non-religious, you
know, non-religious Jews, most non-religious Jews probably
should be okay. Rav Moshe says it's
unclear what a m'challel shabbos befarhesia is
in its definition. Number two. Number three
that for sure that the Rema is
going to be meikel about, you know,
not drinking it if it was poured
but for sure he's not if there's
no intention it's going to be allowed.
But the end of the day what
does seem to be is that we
do, we are machmir about this. Rav
Shlomo Zalman, Rav Elyashiv are machmir about
it. But it seems that there is
what to rely on in these situations
and definitely not to embarrass somebody. To
a goy, to a non-religious Jew. So
if the non-religious Jew comes to your
house and he's taking and pouring the
wine you're like oh gosh you just
traifed up my kitchen you non-religious Jew,
that would be embarrassment. Embarrassment is a
d'oraysa, we're worried about dinei d'rabbanan. There
are times you can embarrass people if
they're doing there's the whole context of
tochacha but not when it's going to
come in the face of embarrassment. So
you have to you know you have
to realize that we are machmir about
it. Rav Shlomo Zalman, Rav Elyashiv are
machmir about it. But it seems that
there is what to rely on in
these situations and definitely not to embarrass
somebody. So next week we'll look at
some of these more practical examples, but
that wraps up some of the more
lamdus behind this topic. All right, we'll
davven maariv. It is very hot in
here. Holy shit. What's the plan? If
there's going to be no air conditioning
anywhere, you know what? Just the mold.
I thought the mold is a nice
added touch. I know next week. Next
week. Next week. Oh I'm in Maine
this week so better be fixed. Fixed.
Bravo! Bravo! בריך שמה דמארי עלמא. ברכו
את ה' המברך. ברוך ה' המברך לעולם
ועד. ברוך ה' המברך לעולם ועד. Amen.
ברוך אתה ה' אלהינו מלך העולם אשר
בדברו מעריב ערבים. והוא חי וקים תמיד
ימלוך עלינו לעולם ועד. ברוך אתה ה'
המעריב ערבים. Amen.